PAUL JAY: Welcome back to Reality Asserts
Itself. I'm Paul Jay on The Real News Network.
We're continuing our series of interviews
with John Kiriakou, the former CIA officer.
And in the last episode, we left on a cliffhanger.
So if you didn't watch the last episode, you'd
better go back and watch. In fact, you probably
should watch all the preceding episodes, 'cause
we're just going to pick it up.
Thanks for joining us again.
JOHN C. KIRIAKOU: Thanks for having me.
JAY: Alright. So what happened next?
KIRIAKOU: Well, as part of my job with the
Senate Foreign Relations Committee, like everybody
else on the committee staff, I had lunch on
a regular basis with foreign diplomats. And
during those lunches, we would talk about
whatever happened to be in the news--Israeli
elections, developments in Turkey, Yemen is
collapsing, whatever happened to be interesting.
And we would just give each other our views
on these news events.
So I was having lunch with a Japanese diplomat
at his invitation at a restaurant on Capitol
Hill. And toward the end of the conversation,
he said to me, so what's next for you? And
I said, well, I'm actually thinking of resigning.
I promised Senator Kerry I'd give him two
years. It's been two and a half. I miss working
for myself. I think I'm going to move on.
JAY: To do what?
KIRIAKOU: I wanted to go back into consulting
again. And he got very excited and he said,
no, don't do that; I can give you money if
you give me information. And I said, do you
have any idea how may times I've made that
pitch? Shame on you for even saying something
like that. I'm going to have to report this.
Well, I went directly from the lunch to the
office of the Senate security officer, and
I said, I was just pitched by a foreign intelligence
officer. So he asked me to write him a memo,
and he would send the memo to the FBI. So
I wrote a very detailed memo about the lunch,
and it went to the FBI.
And then, two days later, two FBI agents came
up to the Senate security office to interview
me. And they said, what we want you to do
is to call him back, invite him to lunch,
and try to get him to tell you exactly what
information he's looking for and how much
money he's willing to pay for it. And we're
going to have two agents at the next table
to listen in on the conversation. I said,
terrific.
So I called him, I invited him to lunch, and
we went to the lunch, and we had another great
conversation, and he told me what he was interested
in. I should add the FBI didn't show up to
sit at the next table. Right before that lunch,
they called and said, just go ahead and do
it and write us at the memo.
JAY: So who's setting you up? The FBI or the
CIA?
KIRIAKOU: Well, I thought that I was helping
out the FBI by helping them identify a foreign
intelligence officer.
So I did this a second time, and a third time,
and a fourth time. And I might have even had
a fifth lunch with him.
Finally, he told me that--.
JAY: But are you thinking this is a setup?
KIRIAKOU: No. No. I thought this was a counterintelligence
investigation.
So, finally he tells me, I'm being transferred
to Cairo. I said, okay, good luck, nice to
meet you, nice to know you, and I never saw
him again.
It wasn't until a year later that we learned
that there was no Japanese intelligence officer,
there was no Japanese diplomat. He was an
FBI agent. And what they were trying to do
was to set me up on a real espionage charge--not
one of the bullshit espionage charges that
they ended up putting on me--all of which
were dropped, I should add. They knew that
their espionage case against me was weak to
nonexistent. I hadn't committed espionage.
In fact, one of the espionage charges--I'm
going to interrupt myself here--one of the
espionage charges was based on the fact that
I had leaked top-secret, compartmented information
about a CIA program to The New York Times.
Do you know what that information was? That
the CIA had a program to capture or kill al-Qaeda
members.
JAY: Come on!
KIRIAKOU: I got an espionage charge for that.
The other two espionage charges were based
on the fact that I had given a former CIA
colleague's business card--and he's no longer
in the CIA, and he was never undercover--I
had given this business card to two reporters,
one at ABC and one at The New York Times.
So I got three espionage charges.
JAY: Wait a sec. If you're not undercover,
there's lots CIA agents--
KIRIAKOU: Precisely.
JAY: --that are officers that are known and
that get talked about.
KIRIAKOU: In fact, when we raised this in
court, my attorney told the judge, your honor,
this man was never undercover, and all my
client did was to pass his business card,
which he's handing out to everybody, to these
two reporters. And the judge said, I find
that very hard to believe. So she turns to
the prosecutors and she says, is that true?
And the prosecutor says, well, Your Honor,
Mr. Kiriakou really should have been more
careful. And she turns to my attorneys and
says, I'll entertain him a motion to dismiss
those charges. So they were all eventually
dropped. But they knew, the FBI knew that
these charges and the espionage case against
me was very weak. So what they wanted to do
was to catch me actually committing espionage.
And so they sent in this pretend Japanese
diplomat.
JAY: Okay. You didn't fall for it, but they
continued to target you anyway.
KIRIAKOU: Right. But, see, all this time,
I didn't know that I was being targeted. When
I had lunch with the Japanese diplomat, this
was 2011. This was the spring of 2011. I wasn't
arrested until 2012.
And what really did me in was in January 2012,
I got a call from the FBI. Hi, this is so-and-so
with the FBI field office in Washington. Do
you remember that case you helped us out with
about a year ago? I said, sure; about the
foreign diplomat? And he said, yeah. I said,
yeah, sure, I remember. He said, well, we've
got a similar case and we really need your
help. Can you come down here? I said, sure.
In fact, I said, anything for the FBI. Well,
come on down on Thursday. I said, terrific.
So I go down on Thursday and meet with these
two FBI agents in a secure vault, a vaulted
conference room. And we're an hour into this
meeting before I realize, wait a minute, this
case is against me. I had no idea.
But I should have known, because another thing
happened that same week. The previous week,
my mother's sister died in Western Pennsylvania.
And so I rented a car and I went to the funeral.
Well, it turned out I also had a hearing in
Ohio, at family court in Ohio, on child support.
So I rented this car, I went to my aunt's
funeral. And then from the funeral in Pennsylvania
I drove to Warren, Ohio, and I checked into
a hotel to wait for the hearing on Monday
afternoon.
So, Monday morning I didn't have anything
to do. I got up and I thought, I'm going to
go look at my grandparents' old house. I haven't
seen it in 15 years. I'm going to drive through
the neighborhood and see what it looks like.
So I drive up to the house, and I'm going,
like, 2 miles an hour. And I notice there's
a Toyota behind me. So I waved an apology
and I sort of pulled over to the side of the
road.
JAY: And they don't want to pass.
KIRIAKOU: They didn't want to pass. And I
thought, well, that's odd. So I drive up to
the intersection and I make this great big
U-turn in the intersection. Well, this guy
makes great big U-turn as well. And I thought,
alright, it's either he's a carjacker or he's
a private eye that my ex-wife hired to follow
me.
So I know the neighborhood well. I cut through
the neighborhood, using what I would have
called a surveillance detection route (I already
knew that I was being followed). And I drive
to the cemetery where my grandparents are
buried. So I stop the car near their graves.
I get out. This guy passes me and parks about
100 feet away and turns around, and he's just
watching me.
JAY: Yeah, they want you to know.
KIRIAKOU: Right. It was pretty clear.
So I called my wife and I said, this is going
to sound crazy, but I'm under surveillance.
And she agreed with me that it was probably
my ex-wife having hired a private eye--to
catch me doing what, I had no idea.
But then from there--.
JAY: [incompr.] wouldn't be so obvious.
KIRIAKOU: Right.
From there I drove to the Packard Museum.
Remember the car, the Packard, from the '40s
and '50s? Well, it was made in that town,
Warren, Ohio. And there's a Packard Music
Hall, and next to it is the Packard Museum.
So I drove into the parking lot of the Packard
Museum and I made a U-turn there. He did the
same. I waited until the light was red, and
then I sped through the red light, and he
got caught up in traffic. And then I just
sort of wended my way back to the motel.
So I thought, well, some local yokel private
eye just got too close and didn't know what
to do 'cause I was driving erratically, and
I didn't think about it. Well, it was after
this meeting with the FBI four days later
that I realized it was the FBI. They had followed
me all the way from Virginia. They probably
thought I was running to Canada or something,
because their call had tipped me off. I didn't
know.
But I realized that next Thursday, in that
meeting, that I'm in deep trouble. In fact,
at the end of the meeting, they said, well,
you should know that as we speak, we're executing
a search warrant on your home. And I said,
am I under arrest? And he said, not yet. And
I said, well, I want to talk to my attorney.
JAY: Triggered by what, according to them?
This meeting with this Japanese--phony Japanese
diplomat?
KIRIAKOU: They decided they couldn't charge
me with that, which they couldn't, 'cause
I hadn't done anything wrong. And they went
ahead and charged me with three counts of
espionage related to the--saying that the
CIA was capturing al-Qaeda leaders, and the
two business cards. So I got three espionage
charges there. They added a charge of making
a false statement to the CIA's Publications
Review Board, which was absurd. That was in
the process of writing my book. They said
that I made a false statement.
I don't even recall what the false statement
was supposed to have been. But I remember
sitting in the conference room with my lawyers,
and they said, so what exactly was the false
statement? And I said, I don't know, I don't
know what this is supposed to be. I was supposed
to have lied to them somehow. Anyway, they
also charged me with one count of violating
the Intelligence Identities Protection Act
of 1982.
JAY: The business card.
KIRIAKOU: No, it was different, because that
guy was never undercover. I had gotten a call
in 2008--so this is four years earlier--I
had gotten a call from a reporter who was
writing a book on the rendition program, and
he wanted to know if I knew anybody that I
can introduce him to that he could interview
for the book. I said, I don't know anybody.
I didn't have anything to do with rendition.
I really never met any of those guys. So he
said, well, what about the guy in your book
that you mention running into at the airport
in Pakistan? And I said, yeah, I can't remember
his name. And he said, I think his first name's
John. And I said, oh, right, that's John Doe
or John Smith. I said, I don't know where
he is. He's probably retired and living somewhere
in Northern Virginia. That was a felony, and
I served two years in prison for that conversation.
JAY: That's the one you actually had to plead
to.
KIRIAKOU: Yes.
So they tried hard to get me. And when I say
hard, I mean they tried to get me 45 years.
JAY: So that's the short of the--to jump to
the chase, you were facing all these espionage
charges,--
KIRIAKOU: Right.
JAY: --and so you plead to this one.
KIRIAKOU: My investigator developed information
indicating that the reporter did not get that
name from me. He got it from a disgruntled
former CIA officer in Bethesda, Maryland.
JAY: So why didn't you fight it?
KIRIAKOU: Well, we went to the prosecutors
to fight it, and the prosecutors said, first
of all, you can't prove that we withheld the
information, you can't prove that we ever
had the information. Secondly, we'll drop
that charge, we'll drop that IIPA charge.
But we're going to go after you on the three
espionage charges.
JAY: But why--they're so ridiculous, the three
espionage charges. Why didn't you fight them?
KIRIAKOU: Because this is the Eastern District
of Virginia. It's called the "Espionage Court".
And nobody ever wins in the Eastern District
of Virginia. This is why I told Ed Snowden
when he first went public, don't come home,
because you won't get a fair trial. Your jury's
going to be made up of FBI agents, military
officers, CIA officers. You're never going
to get a fair hearing here. Never.
So for me it ended up being an economic question:
can my family live without me for two years,
basically on the kindness of strangers and
family members? And the answer was yes. But
could they live without me for 20, which is
what I realistically could have expected if
I had been convicted of the espionage charges?
No, they couldn't have made it for 20. So
I cut my losses and I took a plea.
JAY: It's extortion.
KIRIAKOU: Mhm. But this is what the Justice
Department does. What they do is they heap
charges on you, knowing that they're going
to drop all of them but one if you take a
plea, because what you're eventually going
to do is you're going to be so beaten down
and you're going to spend every cent you have
and every cent you've been able to borrow
from friends or family members, you're going
to spend your pension--unless they take it
away from you like they did in my case--and
you're going to still have these charges.
JAY: They took your pension away from you.
KIRIAKOU: Yeah. I lost my federal pension.
Mhm. I've got nothing. I'm going to have to
work till the day I die. There's nothing I
can do about it.
So what they do is they heap on these charges,
knowing that eventually you're going to give
up and you're going to take a plea. That's
why, according to ProPublica, that actually
studied this, the feds have a 98.2 percent
conviction rate. I said in a speech right
before I went to prison, Saddam Hussein won
98 percent of his last presidential election
and we said the fix was in. The Justice Department
wins 98.2 percent of their cases and we say
they're geniuses. I say there's something
wrong with the system.
JAY: Now, this was all designed to send a
message in the CIA: do not--if you're one
of us, you don't even poke around at all.
And it sounds--the more you tell the story,
it's--almost sounds like it's less about that
you went public on torture, which I'm sure
pisses them off at the time, but the fact
that you keep poking.
KIRIAKOU: Right.
JAY: And number two, to shut you up. This
has not shut you up.
KIRIAKOU: Oh, no.
JAY: In fact, quite the opposite.
KIRIAKOU: No, quite the opposite. In fact,
I said, again, in a speech before I went to
prison, if they thought this would shut me
up, they don't know me at all, because now
I've devoted my life to fighting them.
JAY: Thanks for joining us.
KIRIAKOU: Happy to be here.
JAY: And thank you for joining us on Reality
Asserts Itself on The Real News Network. And
I'm sure John's going to be back on The Real
News, not too distant future.